<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Nouemb. 28. Numb. 9. Briefe abstracts out of diuerse letters of trust Relating the newes of this present weeke, out of Persia, Egypt, Babylon, Barbary, Turkey, Italy, Spaine, Germanie, Silesia, France, and the Low Countries, with diuers passages from the sea. Wherein are remembered the troubles in the Turkish Empire, the strength of the pyrates of Argier, with a touch of the giuing vp of the towne of Glatz, and the holding out of Frankendale. With the victories of Count Mansfield in the land of Embden, and the flight of the Count of that countrey; and the going on of the Prince of Orange towards Lingen. Together with the sea businesses of the Spanish and Hollandish fleetes. In the end is added something of the French affaires, with some other occurrences.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08169</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18507.91</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115600</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850818</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850818</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16046</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08169)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16046)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 905:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Nouemb. 28. Numb. 9. Briefe abstracts out of diuerse letters of trust Relating the newes of this present weeke, out of Persia, Egypt, Babylon, Barbary, Turkey, Italy, Spaine, Germanie, Silesia, France, and the Low Countries, with diuers passages from the sea. Wherein are remembered the troubles in the Turkish Empire, the strength of the pyrates of Argier, with a touch of the giuing vp of the towne of Glatz, and the holding out of Frankendale. With the victories of Count Mansfield in the land of Embden, and the flight of the Count of that countrey; and the going on of the Prince of Orange towards Lingen. Together with the sea businesses of the Spanish and Hollandish fleetes. In the end is added something of the French affaires, with some other occurrences.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B. A[lsop] for Nathaniel Butter, Nicholas Bourne, and William Sheffard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 83.</note>
                  <note>Now = Newsbooks 91.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 83 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Europe --  History --  1517-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16046:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16046:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Nouemb. 28. Numb. 9.</p>
            <p>BRIEFE ABSTRACTS OVT OF DIVERSE LETTERS OF TRVST.</p>
            <p>RELATING The Newes of this preſent Weeke, out of <hi>Perſia, Egypt, Babylon, Barbary, Turkey, Italy, Spaine, Germanie, Sileſia, France,</hi> and the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> with diuers paſſages from Sea.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein are remembred the Troubles in the</hi> Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh Empire, the Strength of the Pyrates of <hi>Argier,</hi> with a touch of the giuing vp of the Towne of <hi>Glatz,</hi> and the holding out of FRANKENDALE.</p>
            <p>With the Victories of Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> in the Land <hi>of</hi> Embden, <hi>and the flight of the Count of that</hi> Countrey; And the going of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> towards <hi>Lingen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Together with the Sea Buſineſſes of the</hi> Spaniſh <hi>and</hi> Hollandiſh <hi>Fleetes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the end is added ſomething of the <hi>French</hi> Affaires, with ſome other <hi>Occurrences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>B. A.</hi> for <hi>Nathaniel Butter, Nicholas Bourne,</hi> and <hi>William Sheffard.</hi> 1622.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:16046:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16046:2"/>
            <head>From <hi>Rome</hi> Octob. <hi>18.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WEe told you before in our Newes, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Nouember</hi> 7. That the Cardinall <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>douici</hi> had purchaſed the Dutchy of <hi>Zaragola,</hi> of the Duke of that place, for 800000. Crownes, which is againe confirmed by letters from <hi>Rome, October</hi> 18. and there is added, that after the Cardinall had gone through with his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe, that the Pope himſelfe went from <hi>Freſcati</hi> to ſee it. At this <hi>Freſcati</hi> the Pope had moſt delicate and admirable deuices of Waterworkes, as forced Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, Springs, Conduits, and the like, the moſt cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in the world.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>From <hi>Rome</hi> Octob. <hi>25.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>In regard that the riuer of <hi>Po,</hi> hath by a late inunda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ouerflowing, done much hurt in the territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of <hi>Bologna</hi> and <hi>Perrara,</hi> with the Biſhopricke of <hi>Farenza;</hi> they haue taken order to looke to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vp and ſtrengthening of their bankes, and the draining of their Sluices thereabouts: And the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall <hi>Capponi</hi> hauing an intention to leade the ſayd riuer in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the water called <hi>Panara,</hi> the proiect is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by the neighbouring Princes, who are likely to ſuſtaine great loſſe if it ſhould goe forward.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:16046:3"/>
            <head>From <hi>Rome</hi> the ſame day.</head>
            <p>From <hi>Meſsina</hi> in <hi>Sicilia</hi> wee heare, That the Prince <hi>Philiberto</hi> hath ſent a Galleon, with eight hundred <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> in it, towards <hi>Vado,</hi> for the State of <hi>Millan:</hi> But the people of <hi>Medena</hi> and <hi>Parmegia</hi> are vp in Armes, to ſtay the paſſage of any Warlike Bands, that ſhould be brought that way; ſeeing that the great Duke of <hi>Tuſcanie</hi> will ſend Forces to the ayde of the Duke of <hi>Mantua,</hi> who feareth an inuaſion from the Duke of <hi>Sauoy,</hi> becauſe there is an Allyance betweene theſe two Dukes; the Duke of <hi>Sauoy</hi> hauing marryed the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours Siſter, and the Emperour hauing lately marryed the Duke of <hi>Mantua's</hi> Daughter.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Salerno</hi> in <hi>Sicilia,</hi> the great Marchants, <hi>Varneſt</hi> and <hi>Como</hi> are broken for 60000 Crownes, and <hi>Iohn Baptiſta</hi> for 80000.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Don Lewis di Marades</hi> is made Great Maſter of <hi>Malta,</hi> in place of the old Maſter, lately decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>From <hi>Venice,</hi> Octob. <hi>22.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>Marcus Antonius de Dominis,</hi> the late Archbiſhop of <hi>Spalato,</hi> hauing lyen at <hi>Antwerpe</hi> ſome whiles, paſſed from thence homewards: and about the 20 of Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber was ſafely gotten to <hi>Millan</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> whence hee goes directly towards <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:16046:3"/>
            <head>From <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> Octob. <hi>3.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>The Letters from thence report theſe particulars following.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That there was arriued there an Embaſſadour out of <hi>Poland,</hi> who came with a ſtately trayne of an hundred followers. His Errand was, for confirmation of the League, and continuation of the Peace, in the Reigne of this preſent Sultan <hi>Muſtapha;</hi> which was after the end of the late Warres, made betweene his King, and the former Sultan <hi>Oſman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, That the purpoſe of making Warres againſt the King of <hi>Perſia</hi> holds ſtill: but that the preparations haue beene much hindered, and there haue fallen out many difficulties, which croſſe the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh intentions: The chiefe of which was, That hee hauing committed moſt of the preparations vnto the Baſhaw of <hi>Babylon,</hi> becauſe his Gouernment lyes next vnto <hi>Perſia;</hi> the Natiues and Subiects of <hi>Babylon</hi> had before made their Baſhaw to diſobey the Great Turkes Commaunds in that point: And when hee ſince ſeemed willing to obey his Lord and Maſter, the <hi>Babylonians</hi> haue taken and burnt their Baſhaw and <hi>Mufti</hi> (the <hi>Mufti</hi> being their chiefe Prieſt or Pope of the Mahometan Religion) and haue ſince choſen to themſelues new Gouernours; whom, if the Grand Seignior ſhall offer to diſturbe, or diſplace, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue to defend themſelues againſt him, and to put themſelues, for the more ſecuritie, vnder the protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Sophi,</hi> or King of <hi>Perſia;</hi> who, for ſome
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16046:4"/> differences in Religion, is ſtill, and now eſpecially, the mortalleſt and powerfulleſt Enemy that the Great Turke hath.</p>
            <p>This is alſo confirmed by other Letters, which came by the way of <hi>Venice:</hi> which affirme alſo, That the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion in <hi>Babylon</hi> is moſt certaine; and that the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw there (I take it, they meane the new Baſhaw of the Peoples chuſing) holds great correſpondencie with the King of <hi>Perſia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, theſe diſturbances in the Eaſterne parts of the Turkiſh Empire, were alſo much encreaſed by a Sedition in <hi>Egypt:</hi> Which Countrey alſo beeing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Turkiſh Dominion, refuſed to accept of their new Baſhaw, and made a moſt furious Faction againſt him; ſo that the whole Countrey was alſo ready to reuolt: but by the perſwaſion of the former Baſhaw, then going out of his Office, the common people were ſomething appeaſed, and entertayned their new Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour.</p>
            <p>And thus you ſee the diſtractions of this huge and vaſte Turkiſh Empire; which begins to change their Obedience, with the Murther of their former Prince: Which Seditions in the people, no doubt will be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly apprehended by the King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> who could willingly ſee euery one of the Baſhawes (like the Captaines after <hi>Alexanders</hi> death) catch a ſhare for himſelfe, that ſo hee might be too ſtrong for any one of them ſingle; and at laſt, whileſt they fight with him ſeuerally, hee might ouercome them all gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:16046:4"/>
            <head>From Algier, Octob. <hi>5.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>From <hi>Algiers</hi> the Letters come by the way of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice,</hi> whence they write; that the two famous En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Pyrats, Captaine <hi>Ward,</hi> and Captaine <hi>Sampſon,</hi> and diuers others of their crew, are lately dead of the plague, which is extremely rife in many parts of <hi>Barbary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From <hi>Algiers</hi> againe they write, that the Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador of the States of the Low Countryes Doctor <hi>Pinacker,</hi> had ſo well ſped himſelfe in his ambaſſage, that he had obtained an agreement betwixt thoſe of <hi>Algier,</hi> and the vnited Prouinces; and that hee had gotten libertie for diuers of his Countrimen, whom the Pyrats of <hi>Algier</hi> had taken at Sea, and made Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley-ſlaues of, which he hauing obtained here, went for the ſame purpoſe towards <hi>Thunis,</hi> to diſcharge thoſe Dutchmen, who were there held either in the Priſons, or in the Galleys.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Algier</hi> againe they write, that the Pyrats had 42. ſaile at ſea, excellently well prouided: And that ſome of them had lately brought in a moſt rich Prize to <hi>Algier,</hi> which was a Spaniſh Carrick bound from <hi>Lisbone</hi> in <hi>Portugall,</hi> for the Eaſt Indies; whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in were found diuers Cheſts of money, of Gold and Siluer, &amp;c. And they brought in alſo another Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Galleon, with 16. braſſe and many yron peeces of Ordnance, manned alſo with 250. Souldiers and Sailers, and beſides both theſe, they had gotten 4. other ſhips alſo.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:16046:5"/>
            <head>From Marſilia, Octob. <hi>27.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Some of the Galleys of <hi>Algiers</hi> haue done great hurt to ours hereabouts, and haue nere to <hi>Tarracona</hi> taken a Spaniſh veſſell comming from <hi>Botri,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother from <hi>Marſilia,</hi> both richly laden; but the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners ſaued themſelues by getting a-ſhoare: But whiles the Pyrats were pillaging the Ships, certaine Spaniſh Galleys came and reſcued them out of their hands.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>From Rome, Octob. <hi>18.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>By the way of <hi>Rome</hi> alſo the newes comes from <hi>Algiers,</hi> that the Turkiſh Pyrates there haue lately taken a ſhip, comming from <hi>Noua Hiſpania,</hi> wherein were to the value of 20000. Crownes, and 200. men which were found aboard of her, were all made ſlaues.</p>
            <p>Thus you heare, that though <hi>Ward</hi> and <hi>Sampſon,</hi> be dead, yet the Turkes haue Pyrates and Rouers enough to trouble all the Merchants that trade that way.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>From Venice, Octob. <hi>28.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>From <hi>Madrid</hi> in <hi>Spaine</hi> we heare, that the Duke <hi>de Alua,</hi> is departed the 20. of the laſt moneth towards <hi>Barcellona,</hi> to take vpon him the Viceroyes place, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the Kingdome of <hi>Naples.</hi> And that there are ſome Commiſſioners of the Kings priuie Counſell appointed to examine the Duke of <hi>Oſsuna,</hi> vpon di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers particulars: This Duke <hi>de Oſſuna,</hi> was the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16046:5"/> Viceroy of <hi>Naples,</hi> and for ſome miſdemeanors brought in disfauour with the King of <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence alſo they write, that the King of <hi>Spaines</hi> Maſter of the leaſe, or of the kings game, is declared Viceroy, or Lord Deputie of <hi>Barcellona,</hi> and Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Millaine.</hi> Further they write, that the Duke of <hi>Paſterona</hi> is made Lord Chamberlaine of <hi>Spaine.</hi> And that the Count of <hi>Monteri</hi> was to haue an Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſage towards <hi>Rome,</hi> with the entertainment of 30000. Crownes of yearely penſion during that ſeruice.</p>
            <p>There is alſo newes, that the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> hath giuen the City of <hi>Matera</hi> vnto <hi>Don Gonzales de Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dua,</hi> with the title of Prince, or Duke, as hee ſhall pleaſe to like beſt of.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>From Genoa, Octob. <hi>29.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Here are arriued 7. Galleys of the Duke <hi>de Oria,</hi> and 4. others belonging to our Common-wealth of <hi>Genoa,</hi> with the Duke <hi>de Alua,</hi> who is landed at <hi>Niſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa:</hi> from whence he diſpatcht a Poſt to the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Millaine,</hi> deſiring him to meet him at <hi>Final</hi> to conferre there together: But the Gouernour an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered him, that hee had yet receiued no order from <hi>Spaine</hi> to leaue <hi>Millaine.</hi> The ſaid Galleyes haue brought a Million of Royalls of 8. out of <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:16046:6"/>
            <head>From Leverno, Octob. <hi>30.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>The good ſhippe called <hi>San Pietro</hi> is here arriued from <hi>Alexandria,</hi> with very rich lading, and alſo the ſhip called <hi>Sancta Maria,</hi> from <hi>Algiers,</hi> which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other commodities, hath brought alſo two ſmall bales of Diamonds.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>From Vienna, Octob. <hi>26.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>On Saturday morning the <hi>Perſian</hi> Ambaſſador comming hither, had Audience the next Sunday, his meſſage is, to continue the league with his Emperiall Maieſtie, which the father to this preſent King of <hi>Perſia</hi> ſo much deſired: It ſeemes this King purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to make himſelfe gracious with the Chriſtians, and to giue certaine Chriſtians of the Greeke religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, freedome of conſcience.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>From Breſlaw in Sileſia, Octob. <hi>27.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>The Plague is ſtill ſo great and raging in the lower <hi>Hungary,</hi> that whole villages dye all vp of it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>From Franckford. Nouemb. <hi>12.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>We haue lately made mention of the ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring vp of the Caſtle of <hi>Manheim</hi> to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, which being performed, the Garriſon marched out thence betwixt nine and eleuen a clocke in the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16046:6"/> forenoone, hauing 10 Companies of Engliſh, and 14 Companies of Dutch, but yet nothing neere whole and full Companies. There were found in the Caſtle 5000 malter or ſacks of corne, and 300 Fuder or Tuns of wine, and 52 peeces of Cannon; but as for powder, and ſuch other prouiſion, nothing at all, for the beſieged had beſtowed that vpon their enemies before.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>From Franckford. Nouemb. <hi>18.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>The ſiege of <hi>Franckendale</hi> yet continues, for they in the Towne being indifferently well prouided, purpoſe not to giue it ouer too ſuddenly, without honourable conditions. The Enemie hath not much dry ground to entrench himſelfe vpon, ſo that the beſieged care not much for him, vntill the hard froſt comes, when the Enemie may both lye dry, and haue firme ground to draw his Ordnance, if the ſiege laſts ſo long, which is expected to be raiſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that time.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>From Hamborough, Nouemb. <hi>12.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Since our laſt newes printed <hi>Nouemb.</hi> 21. wherein we told you of the reſolute holding out of the ſiege of <hi>Glatz;</hi> we haue heard ſince, that that ſtrong towne is ſurrendred to the Emperour, by the young Count of <hi>Tourne,</hi> who before ſo brauely defended it: But the particulars we yet haue not: Only thus much from <hi>Hamborough,</hi> that the young Count was
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16046:7"/> there arriued, with intention to goe into <hi>Holland,</hi> and that he was enforct to giue it vp for want of powder. But of this, the next faire winde, will (we hope) bring vs the particulars. In the meane time, you may pleaſe to obſerue this, that the two ſtrong peeces of <hi>Glatz</hi> and <hi>Manheim,</hi> were much about a time giuen ouer, not for want of valour, but for want of powder.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>From the Dyet of Regenſpurg.</head>
            <p>Here are alſo ſome letters in <hi>London,</hi> which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, that the Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> hath inuaded the Count of <hi>Embdens</hi> country, vpon this quarrell (as it is thought) that he maintayned ten Companies for three months ſpace in <hi>Spinolaes</hi> Armie, againſt the States and the Prince of <hi>Orange:</hi> And that the Marqueſſe <hi>Spinola</hi> hath ſent vp forces to inuade the Duke of <hi>Holſteins</hi> country.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>From Amſterdam, Nouemb. <hi>18.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> (who we told you before in our laſt Newes, was gone vp) is now they ſay gone to take in <hi>Lingen,</hi> which Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> had a farre off blocked vp before. That which may make this paſſe for truth is, for that <hi>Lingen</hi> (as we told you) was ſometimes the Prince of <hi>Oranges</hi> owne inheritance, which he now deſires much to recouer. The Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> is now got into <hi>Embden-land:</hi> He is thought to haue neere 10000 horſe. He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16046:7"/> as they ſay, 200000 Rixe Dollars, and two principall Townes (the very keyes of the country) of the Count of <hi>Emden,</hi> in ſatisfaction to the States, whoſe enemies hee had ayded. Whereupon the Count fled with his houſhold furniture, towards the Biſhop of <hi>Bremens</hi> country, and ſent his two daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to the towne of <hi>Embden</hi> to be there in more ſafetie.</p>
            <p>It is confirmed, that the Count of <hi>Anholt,</hi> who hath beene the Biſhop of <hi>Cullens</hi> Generall, hath had his towne of <hi>Anholt</hi> taken from him by Count <hi>Mansfield.</hi> The country comes in ſo faſt to Count <hi>Mansfield,</hi> that he cannot entertaine them all, but is faine to thanke and diſmiſſe diuers.</p>
            <p>The money which ſhould pay thoſe 16000, which the Colonel <hi>Kniphowſen</hi> is gone to leuie for the Duke of <hi>Brunſwick,</hi> in <hi>Bremenland, Weſphalia,</hi> and <hi>Brunſwick,</hi> is made ouer to <hi>Embden</hi> by the States of the Vnited Prouinces; where it lyes ready for them.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Brunſwick</hi> was conueyed vp towards Count <hi>Mansfield,</hi> by the Count <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Naſſaw</hi> his horſe: which peraduenture were thoſe 30 Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, or ſome of them, which we in our laſt Newes told you of, that Count <hi>Henry</hi> had at <hi>Schenckſconſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We haue here in <hi>London</hi> heard it againe repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> and <hi>Henry Vandenberg</hi> haue had ſome bickering, wherein <hi>Mansfield</hi> had much the better: but for that we wonder, how that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16046:8"/> Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> ſhould go on ſo quietly into <hi>Emb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den-land,</hi> and why the Count ſhould flie, if <hi>Henry Vandenberg</hi> were ſo neere; as alſo for that we haue heard no further of <hi>Henry Vandenbergs</hi> march that way, vnleſſe it be he that is gone into the Duke of <hi>Holſteins</hi> country; we will not report this as a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, till we ſee better authoritie for it, in the Low Dutch relations.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>From the Hague the <hi>26</hi> of Nouemb. <hi>1622.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>The Newes here is, That the Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> is with his forces in the County of <hi>Embden,</hi> ranſacking the country: And that the Biſhop of <hi>Collen,</hi> and others, raiſe alſo forces to doe the like, meaning to reuenge themſelues vpon the Duke of <hi>Holſteins</hi> country, or thereabouts.</p>
            <p>The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> is alſo ready with 12000 men to march vpwards.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:16046:8"/>
            <head>From Duynkercke, the firſt of Nouember.</head>
            <p>Our valiant and famous Captaine <hi>Whitbok</hi> is here deceaſed the ſix and twentieth of <hi>Octob.,</hi> thoſe that employed him haue loſt much by his death, in the iudgement of the whole world: for he was a valiant and wary Captaine. Hee was buried with great ſtate and pompe. <hi>Burgundy</hi> was drawne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde him, his Corpes were wrapped vp, in the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite of a Frier Predicant: the Hearſe was followed by an hundred Muskettiers, who gaue him three vollies before the Church at his buriall. Hee hath left behinde him a Brother of his, who is likewiſe a very valiant Captaine.</p>
            <p>Concerning the tyranny of the Reformed Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers (ſo the <hi>Dunkirkers</hi> here, call the <hi>Hollanders</hi> who profeſſe the Reformed Religion) vpon thoſe of Captaine <hi>Michael Iacobs</hi> Ship of <hi>Oſtend,</hi> whom they fiſht and gate out of the water, to hang them, it will breed ill bloud, for wee are aduiſed from <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> that the ſeuenty <hi>Rotterdammers</hi> and <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huyſeners,</hi> which are here in priſon, muſt caſt Dice for their liues, to make vp two and twenty out of them all, to be hanged; which are iuſt ſo many as the <hi>Hollanders</hi> hanged of ours. And our Princeſſe the Archducheſſe ſhewes her ſelfe very mercifull, ſeeing ſhee will haue but number for number put to death; and not all of theſe, which are here im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned.</p>
            <p>Touching the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Nauie, ſeeing it is not arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued here with the laſt good winde, we thinke that it is returned backe againe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:16046:9"/>
            <head>From Fluſhing the <hi>22.</hi> of Nouember.</head>
            <p>After the finiſhing of this Letter, here comes certaine tidings by a man of warre, that the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fleete ſome foure and twenty or ſeuen and twenty Saile ſtrong, is vpon the Coaſt of <hi>France,</hi> betwixt <hi>Boloigne</hi> and <hi>Diepe,</hi> being reſolued to land fiue thouſand <hi>Spaniards</hi> in <hi>Flanders.</hi> Whereupon wee are here in all haſte making diuers ſaile ready, ten lying ready in the Hauen, went preſently away.</p>
            <p>It was ſome whiles ſince reported here in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> had alreadie landed theſe fiue thouſand men in <hi>France,</hi> to goe from thence into <hi>Flanders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now if you pleaſe to ſee what warlike pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations the Low-country-men haue lately made, againſt the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Nauie, you may reade theſe three particulars, which though they be not al new, becauſe not all done at once; yet we thought good to impart them, for that we would ſhew you their whole Fleet, or as much of it as we know.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>From Amſterdam the eleuenth of October.</head>
            <p>Two daies agoe all the ſhips which were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed at <hi>Dordrecht, Rotterdam,</hi> and <hi>Ganda,</hi> ſailed towards the <hi>Blaeke,</hi> which lyeth vpon the way of <hi>Breda,</hi> what, and whither they intend wee doe not know.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>From Amſterdam the <hi>22.</hi> of Octob.</head>
            <p>Seeing the newes of the comming of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fleet continueth, they are arming here diuers great
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16046:9"/> and ſmall Veſſels to goe meet the ſame, and to this effect there are likewiſe diuers Merchants ſhips arreſted in <hi>Texel,</hi> and ſome <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> ſhips are euen diſcharged, to doe the like ſeruice.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>From the Hage the <hi>28.</hi> of October.</head>
            <p>It is agreed againe that the Poll-money ſhall bee paid in this Countrey againe, beſide the fiue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth penny of euery ones eſtate.</p>
            <p>Yeſterday there came certaine Letters vnto his Excellencie, and the States Generall, whereupon they conſulted, and reſolued to ſet preſently an hundred ſaile forth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <head>The Harangue or Speech made vnto the King, by the Deputed Committies of the Reformed Churches of <hi>France,</hi> and the Soueraigntie of <hi>Bearne.</hi>
            </head>
            <sp>
               <p>SIr, We are ſent in the name of all the Reformed Churches in <hi>France,</hi> and the Soueraigntie of <hi>Bearne,</hi> to beſeech your Maieſtie in all humbleneſſe, to grant them Peace, Our hearts and mindes being more humbled than our bodies do proſtrate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues before your feet to craue the ſame; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt moſt humbly your Maieſtie to beleeue, that the falſe reports which were ſpred abroad amongſt vs of the deſignes of your Maieſty againſt our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, haue caſt vs into this preſent miſery and miſhap: We intend not to colour or excuſe our faults: We confeſſe our ſelues guiltie, and therefore preſent our ſelues here before your Maieſtie to ſue
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16046:10"/> for pardon, and intreat your highneſſe moſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous fauour, beſeeching you to imitate God, whoſe Image you are, and to conſider our infirmities, and to attribute ſomething to the feare which we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued by the falſe preſages of the oppreſſion of the libe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty of our conſciences, and how much the more cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pable your Maieſtie ſhall finde vs, ſo much will your clemencie be more gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rious and renowned.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> the Great, your Father, of happy memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, hath vſed our ſeruice, did rely his truſt vpon vs, and loued vs We beſeech your Maieſty moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, that like as you are Heire of his Royal Vertues, you will be ſo likewiſe of the good will, which hee bare vnto vs, and not otherwiſe to diſtinguiſh vs hereafter, from your other Subiects, then by that ſeruice, which wee ſhall performe vnto your Highneſſe. For hereby it is, that we hope to ſhew that none can be more than wee, your moſt obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and moſt loyall Subiects and Seruants.</p>
               <p>Vpon this Oration and ſubmiſſion followed the Kings Proclamation, which being not as yet prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in our language, wee here giue you as fit to be added to the former things, of that ſubiect.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <head>The Proclamation of the King, concerning the Peace, publiſhed at <hi>Paris</hi> the one and thirtieth day of October <hi>1622.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <p>Printed at <hi>Paris</hi> by <hi>I. Morel</hi> and <hi>Peter Mettayer,</hi> Ordinary Printers to the King, <hi>1622.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <byline>By the King.</byline>
            <p>IT is made knowne by theſe preſents, that his Maieſtie hauing been pleaſed of his bountie and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16046:10"/> clemencie, to grant peace to his Subiects of the pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ded Reformed Religion (after the aſſuran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> vnto his Highneſſe in their behalfe, for their com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cie and loyaltie hereafter) willeth and commandeth expreſſely all his Subiects, of what qualitie and condition ſoeuer they be, to keepe and obſerue inuiolably the Peace in all places and parts of his Kingdome, Countries, Lands, and Seignio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries within his Dominion: and to liue hereafter in good vnion, friendſhip and concord, according to the Edicts and Proclamations, without any contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention, or prouocation of any, either by deede or word, directly, or indirectly, either of one ſide or the other, in regard of matters paſt and happened, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the late commotions, which his Maieſtie will haue aboliſhed and forgotten: The infringers and refractory perſons ſhall be puniſhed as diſturbers of the common quiet and Tranquillitie, by the Iudges and Officers which are to cenſure them, and to enquire in ſuch caſes, whom his Maieſtie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands and ordaines, to vſe all diligence and good endeuour, to the ſaid effect. Willing alſo to the ſaid end, this preſent Proclamation to be read and publiſhed in all the quarters of his Campe, and in all the Towns and places of his Kingdome, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and Territories vnder his obedience. And becauſe none ſhould pretend ignorance, and that euery one may conforme himſelfe hereunto,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>This is giuen in the Campe before <hi>Mompellier,</hi> 
                  <date>the eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth day of <hi>October,</hi> 1622.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>It was Signed, <hi>Lewis,</hi> and Lower <hi>De Lomenie.</hi>
               </signed>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:16046:11"/>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>The one and thirtieth day of October 1622. this Proclamation and Commandement of the King, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere abo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e written, hath beene by me (who haue ſet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hand h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re vnder) a ſworne and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ier o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Kings, read and publiſhed with the ſound of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>mpet, and publicke crie thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Cittie, and Suburbs of <hi>Paris,</hi> and affixed on the vſuall pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s: b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing accompanied with <hi>Mathurin Noyret</hi> a ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orn Trumpet, and three other Trumpeters.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Signed <hi>Le D.</hi>
                  </signed> Vpon this agreement and the Kings pleaſure certainly knowne, heare what followed.</closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>From Lions the <hi>23.</hi> of October</head>
            <p>The gates of <hi>Mompellier</hi> haue beene now many daies ſet open, and many ſicke and hurt, are out of the Kings Campe, conueyed into the Citie. Both the Queenes are as yet here, and in health.</p>
            <p>Yeſterday and the day before are here arriued diuers of the Kings ſouldiers ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Champaigne,</hi> vnder the command of the Duke of <hi>Angouleſme,</hi> who is reſolued to conduct them vnto his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie to get their pay, but it is thought our Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour will not ſuffer them to goe further.</p>
            <p>They are lodged here in the Suburbs and the neighbouring villages, where they doe g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eat hurt amongſt the country people, which would they were deliuered of their gueſts.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
